<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Light sown for the righteous, and gladness for the upright in heart This is to go abroad among all people who are honest-hearted, especially amongst the inhabitants in Fourns Fells, in Lancashire, and among all who have known me after the flesh, that all honest people may see what I was in profession, and also what I now am by the grace of God. From him which hath come through great tribulations, who hath even left all for Christ, and hath not whereon to lay his head, but is forsaken of father and of mother, and of kinred also, even for the testimony of Jesus, and for the Word of God, whom the world calls, Thomas Rawlinson.</title>
            <author>Rawlinson, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831963</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831963</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36430</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58143)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36430)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2131:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Light sown for the righteous, and gladness for the upright in heart This is to go abroad among all people who are honest-hearted, especially amongst the inhabitants in Fourns Fells, in Lancashire, and among all who have known me after the flesh, that all honest people may see what I was in profession, and also what I now am by the grace of God. From him which hath come through great tribulations, who hath even left all for Christ, and hath not whereon to lay his head, but is forsaken of father and of mother, and of kinred also, even for the testimony of Jesus, and for the Word of God, whom the world calls, Thomas Rawlinson.</title>
                  <author>Rawlinson, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Simmons, at the Bull and Mouth neer Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: This is to go abroad into my countrey, amongst the inhabitants in Fornes Fells, and among all honest people that have known me after the flesh, that all people may see what I was in profession, and what I now am by the grace of God.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the John Rylands University Library of Manchester.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36430:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36430:1"/>
            <p>LIGHT SOWN FOR THE RIGHTEOUS, AND GLADNESS For the Upright in HEART.</p>
            <p>This is to go abroad among all people who are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt-hearted, eſpecially amongſt the Inhabitants in <hi>Fourns Fells,</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and among all who have known me after the fleſh, that all honeſt people may ſee what I was in Profeſſion, and alſo what I now am by the Grace of God.</p>
            <p>From him which hath come through great tribulations, who hath even left all for Chriſt, and hath not whereon to lay his head, but is forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Father and of Mother, and of Kinred alſo, even for the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Jeſus, and for the Word of God, whom the world calls, <hi>Thomas Rawlinſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luk. 14.26, 27.</hi>
                  </bibl> If any man come to me, and hate not his Father, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Wife, and Children, and Brethren, and Siſters, yea, and his own life alſo, he cannot be my Diſciple.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> neer <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36430:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:36430:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36430:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36430:3"/>
            <head>This is to go abroad into my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, amongſt the Inhabitants in <hi>Fornes Fells,</hi> and among all honeſt people that have known me after the fleſh, that all people may ſee what I was in profeſsion, and what I now am by the Grace of God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riends and Neighbors, ye know (if ye will but teſtifie) how that I walked from my youth upwards, after the ſtraiteſt Sect of Religion, harmleſs and blameleſs, inſomuch that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did admire me, and was as touching the rghteouſneſs of the Law, acording to the Letter, blameleſs, as ye know, if ye will teſtifie; without boaſting I ſpeak it; for I exceeded many of my equals in profeſſion, with a ſhew of righteouſneſs, and was exceedingly zealous for the chiefeſt Prieſts in this Nation of <hi>England;</hi> &amp; ſome of you have ſaid, Ye thought that ye needed never deſire to have been in a better condition then I was in, when I was where ye are, without God, and without Chriſt in the World, with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his Name in my mouth, but did not know Chriſt in me, the true Light, who lightneth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the World, ſo was ignorant of the Foundation of God, which ſtandeth ſure, the Light, Chriſt, who lightneth every man; the ſure Foundation-ſtone, which is already laid for a Foundation, that whoſoever buildeth thereon, ſhall never be aſhamed; and being ignorant of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36430:4"/>
of God, I went about to eſtabliſh my own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo did not ſubmit to the Righteouſneſs of God, but got up into a profeſſion of knowing the Lord, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a fair ſayer, but not a doer of the will of God, like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the chief Prieſts, for they ſay, and doth not the things that they ſay; Wo unto them, blind guides, who turn the innocent and the poor out of the way, and cauſes the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to erre by their lyes, and by their lightneſs, and will not that any ſhould turn from the darkneſs to the light. Wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them who gather people into a profeſſion of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, but not into the light, life and power, ye all profeſſing Chriſt to come, and knows not that Chriſt is in you; ſo ye know not where he is, nor how he is in you; I ſpeak this to your ſhame, people of all profeſſions.</p>
            <p>And though I had reformed in many things, and had left off practicing many Idolatrous and Heatheniſh Cuſtoms, which I ſaw to be evil in the ſight of the Lord, as my mind came to be turned to that of God in my conſcience while I yet followed the Prieſts; but being ignorant of that which did let me ſee my own unprofitableneſs, and that all that is in the World is but vanity, I came ſhort, &amp; did not follow on to know the Lord, but choſe rather to follow the Prieſts, &amp; gave no heed to the Word of the Lord vvhich call d behind, Return, return, thou art but a dead man in the Earth; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, lo, this is the way, walk in it; turn in hither to the Word which is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart; this is the Way; but while I followed the Prieſts, they never directed me to this, To the Word which is nigh, in the mouth, and in the heart, nor never exhorted people to the light which Chriſt hath enlightned every man withal: While I followed the Prieſts (I ſay) I never heard them bring this Doctrine to the people, which the true Miniſters of Chriſt bring, and brought, who turn people from the darkneſs to the light, and from the power of Satan unto God: For in the light of the Lord which did ſhine into my conſcience, I came to ſee the deceit of the Prieſts, the Meſſengers of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, who labour to keep people in the darkneſs, in blindneſs
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36430:4"/>
from the light, who would perſwade the people that the light which Chriſt hath enlightned every man withall, is but a natural light, and not ſufficient to give the knowledge of God, or to convince of all ſin, and ſo they wreſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and adds thereto, and ſets up their own Traditions, and makes the Commandments of God of no effect, and void by their own Traditions, and cryes againſt the Light vvith reproachful and ſenſual vvords, leſt the people ſhould believe in the Light, and come to the Light vvhich gives the Knovvledge of God; and ſo long as I remained ignorant of that vvhich did convince me of ſin, and of unbelief, which did let me ſee that I was alſo out of the vvay of God, with the Prieſts, in error and in the darkneſs, ſo long I was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the living and true God, and knevv not hovv he vvas in me ſo knew him not at all but by the hearing of the ear, though I had got the Bible and Books, and a large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, read the Scriptures often, and Books many, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the chiefeſt Prieſts dayly, and vvould fain have gained the Knovvledge of God by them, but could not find it while I follovved the Prieſts, &amp; had thought that they ſhould teach the people knovvledge; but I novv ſee that it is not ſo, and that the Lord hath curſed the Prieſts and their bleſſings, and that no people upon the Face of the Earth, ſhall ever profit by them; the Lord hath ſaid it, (mark it) vvho can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye nor repent: So let God be true and all men lyars; for that vvhich may be knovvn of God, is manifeſt in them, and God hath ſhevved it to them, ſo it is evident; That no man knovvs the Father nor the Son, but as he comes into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to that of God in him, the Light; for the Letter vvithout, nor the Prieſts vvithout, nor any thing vvithout, can never make the comers thereunto perfect, nor give any man the knovvledg of God though he may get the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures into his Head, and ſhall read them often; for no man knovvs the Father but he to whom the Son reveals him.</p>
            <p>Yea, ſo deſirous I vvas to find out the true knovvledge of the pure God, that I ceaſed not to ſeek it night and day with Tears, and cryed out, <hi>How ſhall I come to the living knowledg
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36430:5"/>
ſo God? which is the way where Chriſt may be found, that I may come to know him, even as I am known of him and find him?</hi> The Prieſts ſaid, <hi>That reading the Scriptures and godly Books</hi> (as they called them) <hi>and praying, and following them, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them preach, that this was the way where Chriſt is to be found:</hi> So I did run from one Prieſt unto another, to ſee if haply I could find Chriſt among any of them, for ſeveral years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but did not vvhilſt I followed the Prieſts; ſo all my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vvas in vain; I ſpent my labour for that which is not Bread, and my ſtrength for that which could not ſatisfie; yea, I did read the Scriptures often, &amp; bought the beſt books I could hear of, and read them, and prayed earneſtly always, but did not obtain nor prevail, though I cryed and vvept much, and the reaſon is, becauſe I ſought (unto a people that cannot profit) for the Lord in a vvay vvhere he is not to be found, in the vvay of the ungodly; for God hears not ſinners, and the prayer of the vvicked is ſin, but the prayer of the righteoas is his delight; and vvhile I remained ſervant to ſin, the Lord did not regard my prayer, for it is his own that praiſes him, unto whom his ears is opened alvvays, vvhich he hears and hath regard unto. So I ſee that the Prieſts are lyars, vvho vvould be Teachers of others, and yet knovvs not vvhat they ſay, nor vvhereof they affirm, vvho vvould perſwade you to follow them, and to uphold them in their covetous practiſes, and tells people that hearing them is the right vvay, and obſerving their traditions and cuſtoms is the right vvay, and believing in a Chriſt vvithout you, and looking for a Chriſt without you, is the right vvay; ſo are thoſe vvhich Chriſt ſpake of ſhould come in the laſt dayes, ſaying, <hi>Lo here is Chriſt, and lo there is Chriſt,</hi> but ſaid he, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, nor go not after them;</hi> for Friends, that which may be knovvn of God, is manifeſt in you; ſo til you return to that of God in you, the light, ye are in the darkneſs, out of the good vvay, in an evil vvay, in a vvay that is not good, whatſoever ye and your Prieſts may ſay of it; Neighbors and Friends, I ſpeak by experience what I have ſeen and known, that ſpeak I unto you in the Name of the Lord, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36430:5"/>
ye may take warning betime; for there is no other way to know Chriſt, but in the light wherewith ye are enlightned; ſo if you will own the right way where God dwells, &amp; where he is to be found, ye muſt then return in to the Light, to that which may be known of God in you, and be in love with the Light, for God is Light; he that loves the Light, brings his deeds to the Light, and comes to the light, Chriſt; <hi>Know ye not how that Chriſt is in you except ye be reprobates?</hi> You that talk and prate, and ſay ye believe in a Chriſt without you, who are profeſſing a God and a Chriſt without you, and that he ſaves his people from their ſins, What is this to you who knows not that Chriſt is in you? There ſhall ye find him, if ever ye know him a Saviour to you, who is come a light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, that all men through him might believe; This is he who ſuffered and dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and no other Chriſt I own: I ſay, What is this to you who are yet in your ſins, and doth not believe that ever ye ſhall be made free from ſin while ye are here, but that ye ſhall ſin while ye live? Have ye not learned this of your Prieſts? for this is their Doctrine which they bring you from their Father the Devil, and yet you be believe it, and receives it: So what is this to you, for you to ſay Chriſt ſaves his people from their ſins? for ye bear vvitneſs againſt your ſelves that he is not your Saviour who are yet in your ſins; for ye deny the Work of God, and reſiſt it in your ſelves, and denies the end of Chriſt coming into the World, which is to ſave his people from their ſins, who is come into the World a light, and is manifeſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Works of the Devil; and ſin is the Work of the Devil which Chriſt comes to deſtroy; and you that ſay ye muſt ſin while ye live, ye bear witneſs againſt your ſelves that Chriſt is not yet come to you; ſo ye are the ſervants of ſin, and are free from righteouſneſs; ſo what is Chriſt to you? and what is your profeſſion vvorth?</p>
            <p>So whileſt I followed the Prieſts, I never knew the way how to come to Chriſt, therefore I had no reſt in my ſpirit day nor night from God, while I followed the Prieſts, but Wrath, and Horror, and Judgement purſued me for diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36430:6"/>
to that of God in my conſcience and trouble on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hand; on the right hand and on the left, was ſorrovv and vexation of ſpirit and my heart within me did faint for fear; I vvas even at my Wits-end, and had almoſt deſpaired of hope and of comfort, had not God preſerved me though I knew him not; for I could find no aſſurance of the love of God to my ſoul, while I follovved the Prieſts, though then I could (vvith the Prieſts) talk of high attainments and could alſo with them, and with profeſſors, ſometimes boaſt of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, and alſo of joy and peace ſometimes, when I was lifted up into the airie imaginations with them; and ſo for a while I gloried in the fleſh with prieſts &amp; people and made merry over the Witneſs of God in me; then was Satan ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above all that was called God in me; and then both Prieſts and people did love me, and and ſpake well of me; for the World loves its own; and the Devil who fills his children with mirth and joy, with ſports and pleaſures, and with the glory of this World; he will ſuffer his ſervants to have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth, and to boaſt of God to be their Father; and of Chriſt to be their Saviour, and alſo to talk of faith, and of righteouſneſs, and the like ſo that he can but main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Works in them; which is, To lye, and to ſwear; to be angry, to envy, and to hate, and to be proud and covetous; and to oppreſs, to diſſemble, and to deceive, and to defraud, and to cozen; to fight, to rail, and to be drunk; to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and to be high-minded, being filled with all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which be the Works of the Devil, as luſt, murder, back-biting, evil-ſpeaking, and all deceit, vvhich are the Works of the fleſh: So I ſay, If the Devil have but the heart, and can but keep his Seat there, he cares not then vvhat profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they be of; he knovvs them that they are his, though they may ſay they defie the Devil and all his Works, whoſe minds Satan hath blinded, that they cannot ſee his Works in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves brought forth, which bears witneſs againſt them that they are of their Father the Devil, whoſe Works they do, yet with their mouth, and with their lips and tongue will profeſs that they love God, who have the high ſwelling
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36430:6"/>
Words of hypocriſie, ſo have a zeal without knowledge, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a profeſſion of God in hypocriſie, until the day of ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den deſtruction from God fall upon them for their Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſweep them all into the pit of blackneſs for ever, who are Workers of iniquity both Prieſts and people.</p>
            <p>All-along while I followed the Prieſts, there was ſomething in me of God I ſee (though I knew it not) which did wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt all unrighteouſneſs, &amp; did reprove me if I did but ſwear, or tell a lye, which did not ſpeak peace to me in thoſe things, but I was judged by that of God in me when I did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unrighteous thing; ſo ſtood condemned in my ſelf when I had but an evil thought of doing Wrong, which was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to have preſerved me from all evil if I had but been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient; but being ignorant of it (what it was) gave no heed unto it, but went on in a Way that is not good; ſo did not believe in the light, though I had the light; neither was obedient to the light, though the light did convince me: So I had no peace from God, though in the World I had peace, and with the VVorld was at peace, yet in Chriſt <hi>I</hi> had no peace while I was of the VVorld; for that of God in me cryed againſt me Deſolation, VVo, and Miſery; for God ſeeth not as man, neither canſt thou hide thy ſelf in ſecret and he not ſee thee: So I came to ſee that notwithſtanding all the ſhew in the fleſh I had profeſt of knowing the Lord, I was but a hypocrite when I came in deed and in truth to ſearch &amp; try my ways honeſtly, and to prove my ſelf in truth and in plainneſs, then I did ſee that I was out of the VVay of truth, knew not the truth, though I had the Words of truth in my mouth; ſo was ignorant of God, &amp; ſo the peace which I had did then flye away, it was as it were but for a moment, the Worlds peace which the greedy Prieſts ſpeak unto the people that ſtop into their mouths; they cry peace, peace, when there is no peace from God, where the Lord hath not ſpoken peace; ſo would heal the hurt of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of my people (ſaith the Lord ſleightly) who daub with untempered morter; for from the Prophet, even unto the Prieſt, every one dealeth falſly and deceitfully, and all are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36430:7"/>
to covetouſneſs, both Prieſts and people: So whileſt I followed the Prieſts, I ſee that I was but a fair ſayer, made clean the outſide of the Cup and the Platter, and appeared righteous outwardly unto man, as Neighbors and Friends ye know, who knew me after the fleſh, That I was (as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the righteouſneſs of the Law) blameleſs, and had a zeal for God (though not according to knowledge) by fair Words, profeſſing the Subſtance, but had not the Evidence, the Seal of the Spirit of God to my Spirit; ſo being ignorant of Gods righteouſneſs, (as I ſaid before) which is by the Faith of the Son of God, knowing this, That without righteouſneſs no man can enter into the Kingdom of God; ſo I went about to eſtabliſh my own righteouſneſs, looking for a righteouſneſs without me, that I might appear righteous unto man, being ignorant of the righteouſneſs of faith, which ſaith on this wiſe, (as it is written) <hi>Say not in thy heart, Who ſhall aſcend into Heaven? That is to bring Chriſt down from above; or who ſhall deſcend into the deepe? That is to bring Chriſt again from the dead:</hi> But what ſaith it? <hi>The Word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayeſt do it; that is, the Word of Faith which we preach,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle, who was a Miniſter of God: But unto this Word I was not obedient while I followed the Prieſts, neither knew I it, though it was near; for none of the Prieſts (from the leaſt even unto the chiefeſt) did ever direct my mind unto the Word of Faith which is nigh, in the mouth, and in the heart, to take heed unto, as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place until the day dawn, and the day ſtar ariſe in my heart: So they are the falſe Prophets and Deceivers who is come in ſheeps clothing, making merchandiſe of ſouls for diſhoneſt gain: And theſe are they vvhich Chriſt ſaid ſhould come in the laſt dayes; vvhich <hi>John</hi> ſaw was come in his dayes, vvhich all the World vvondered after, and that all the World is gone after them; ſo they run, yet never was ſent of God to turn people from darkneſs to the light, vvho divine for money, and ſpeak a Divination of their ovvn brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord. So I ſought
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36430:7"/>
to find the living among the dead vvhile I ſought unto the Prieſts; ſo followed a people which cannot profit, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered from Mountain to Hill to find the living, even from one ſort of Prieſts and people unto another, that had the greateſt ſhew of godlineſs; one ſort ſaid, <hi>Lo here is Christ;</hi> and another ſort of profeſſors ſaid, <hi>Lo here;</hi> and glad would I with all my heart to have found him among them, that I might come to find a reſt for my weary ſoul; but Chriſt I found not among any of them, though I did find that ſome ſort of profeſſors could talk much more of Chriſt with their lips then others could do, and had his Name in their mouth oftener then others, having many good Words vvhereby they do beguile ſouls, even with the enticing Words of mens Wiſdom, pretending much towards Chriſt, but are as vain and wanton as they vvho have not ſo great a ſhew in Words towards Chriſt; and though in Words they profeſs that they know him, yet in Works they do deny him; ſo are the greateſt Deceivers of all, vvho have the greateſt ſhew of godlineſs, when their Works are as bad, and their lives too, as them who have no ſhew of godlineſſe at all; for Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits;</hi> ſo vvhen I came to prove them, and to try them by their fruits, I did find them to be as bad as others vvho have not ſo great a ſhew of righteouſneſs; ſo it is not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord; nor proud boaſters in another mans line of things made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to their hand, vvho ſteal their Words from their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, that ſhall enter into life, but he that doth the Will of God; for they make themſelves manifeſt that they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, and without Chriſt, as by their Fruits; I knew them then to be deceitful Workers, though vvith fair ſpeeches and good Words they deceive the ſimple, and ſo blinds the minds of them that believe not in the light. And though I did like the chief Prieſts, and the chief Profeſſors Words then vvell, (ſo far as they was according to the Scriptures of Truth) yet <hi>I</hi> would not reſt ſatisfied ſo, but proved their Works, and laboured to ſee vvhat lives they lived. Whether their Words and their Works agreed in one, yea or nay; and vvhen <hi>I</hi> tryed both the chief Prieſts and the chiefeſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36430:8"/>
their Lives, Works, and Converſation, <hi>I</hi> then ſaw that they are not vvhat they profeſt themſelves to be, ſo could not but for conſcience-ſake deny them; For <hi>I</hi> ſaw them to be hypocrites, lyars cozeners &amp; diſſemblers, &amp; how that a ſmall thing vvould even eaſily provoke any of them to anger, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, vvrath and malice, and ſome to fighting; being heady, high-minded, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God: So <hi>I</hi> could not but turn from them vvho have a Form of godlineſs, but denies the power thereof, as by their Fruits <hi>I</hi> know them; For vvhoſoever ſeeks to be juſtified by Chriſt, and yet they themſelves are found ſinners, is Chriſt therefore the Miniſter of ſin? God forbid; For Chriſt comes to deſtroy the Works of the Devil; he is manifeſt to take away ſin, for in him is no ſin; he that abibeth in Chriſt, ſinneth not. So Friends and Neighbors ſee where ye all are, doteing upon a people which cannot profit you at all, nor help, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but ſhall be a ſhame and a reproach.</p>
            <p>And vvhen <hi>I</hi> vvas turned to the light of Chriſt, J came to ſee the Prieſts deceit, who will not that any of you ſhould come to the light, leſt the people ſhould ſee their Wickedneſs, and ſo to turn from them: And though both prieſts and profeſſors have the Name of the Lord in their mouths, and ſeems to take delight in drawing near to him with their lips, yet their hearts are far from him: So in vain they Worſhip God, who live not the life of the Son of God, but are alive unto ſin; For all whoſe VVords, and Life, and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are not as becomes the Goſpel of Chriſt, are Hypocrites and falſhearted ones, whoſe VVords and VVorks are not one, ſo are VVorkers of iniquity, and doth not the truth, both prieſts and people who live not unto Chriſt: So when J had found out the wickedneſs of the prieſts, and ſaw them ſo filthy, J cryed out for ſorrow, being filled with ſorrow and grief that J could not find a righteous man amongſt them, not one that could direct me into the right VVay, nor was able to teach me the Knowledge of God, though J ran from prieſt to prieſt, and did write to ſeveral of the chiefeſt of them concerning my condition, and have thought that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36430:8"/>
the prieſts lips ſhould preſerve the peoples Knowledge, and that the people ſhould go unto them for Knowledge; but miſerable comforters are they all, none of them could ſpeak a VVord of Comfort to my ſoul; ſo my weary ſoul did even mourn, and cry out in pain for deliverance from under the power of death and hell, and Satan. So J found no way of deliverance while J followed the Prieſts, though they cryed peace, peace unto me, and would perſwade me to be in a good condition, and the like, ſo would have healed me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully, and would have daubed me with untempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, crying peace, peace, where the Lord hath not ſpoken peace, ſo my ſoul refuſed to be comforted by them and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>None but Chriſt; None but Chriſt;</hi> and yet there was none among them that could ſhew me where he is to be found: So being weary in ſpirit, J wandered with a ſad heart and wounded ſpirit, from prieſt to prieſt, ſeeking reſt for my weary ſoul, but found none while J followed after them; wo, wo, wo unto them may all people ſay, that ever ſuch prieſts was born, who have made the hearts of the righteous ſad by their lyes, and by their lightneſs, who ſtands up amongſt the people, pretending to teach them the way how that they may come to the Knowledge of God, yet never was ſent of God; nor none of them unto this day (that ever J knew of) did ever direct people unto the right way, to that of God in them, where they might come to the Knowledge of God, and ſo to know him, whom to know is life eternal; neither do they know it themſelves, ſo are not able to teach others; nay they are ſo far from perſwading people unto the good way, that they ſtand up to reſiſt it, and ſet themſelves againſt it: Jf any who have found the right way, and knows the Lord, be moved of the Lord in bowels of compaſſion unto the people, to go to the Steeplehouſe to ſet before them the right way where God is to be found, a way wherein they have found God; the prieſts they cry to the people, <hi>Away with them, Deceivers, Deceivers,</hi> yet dares not ſtand to prove before the people who be the deceivers by plain Scripture; ſo they are thoſe which Chriſt ſaid would neither enter into
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36430:9"/>
the Kingdom of God themſelves, nor will they ſuffer them that would to enter: For that which may be known of <hi>God</hi> is manifeſt in them, and God hath ſhewed it to them, and bleſſed are they that are faithful.</p>
            <p>Often-times J even wept bitterly when J conſidered theſe things, and was even preſſed to the ground with ſorrow and heavineſs when J could not find any ſatisfaction among no ſort of people; ſo fear ſurpriſed me, &amp; pain took hold on me, as upon a VVoman in travel; trouble without, and horror and wrath within; for the wrath of God was revealed againſt me from heaven, for diſobedience to the pure light within me; and J was even afraid of the judgements of God, leſt the Lord would cut me off, and make me an example to all about me, in that J continued ſo long following the prieſts after that he had ſhewed me how deceitful they all are, and that no people ſhould ever profit by them, and that they are altogether uſeleſs Veſſels, in whom the Lord hath no pleaſure, but his wrath is againſt them, and againſt all ſuch who follow after them: Yet after all this, though the Lord had ſhewed them to me, J was ſomewhat rebellious, and did not turn from them immediately after J was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc't of their wickedneſs, and ſaw that they was never ſent of God, and yet would fain have continued following after them, though J knew J could not profit by them; and notwithſtanding all that the Lord had ſhewed me concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, becauſe J knew that my Kinred according to the fleſh would be ſore ſet againſt me, and riſe up againſt me, and that J ſhould ſuffer much from them, ſo J would faine have followed them to pleaſe my parents, and ſo J began to diſtruſt and queſtion what the Lord had ſhewed me, J then being at that time a ſtranger to the life of God ſo knew not the Lords voice, neither did J underſtand him often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vvhen he ſpoke unto me in the ſpirit, being carnal; yet the love of the Lord vvas ſo much tovvards me, that he gave me not over to a reprobate mind, neither did he deal vvith me according to my ſtubbornneſs, but according to the multitude of his mercies; ſo the long-ſuffering and patience
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36430:9"/>
of God led me to repentance, and then J came clearly to ſee that it was the Lord indeed that appeared unto me, and had ſet theſe things before me, and not man, that had ſo long called unto me, though then J knew him not; but when J knew indeed that it was the Lord that ſpoke unto me, J then gave up all willingly, and left off frequenting all ſorts of people, &amp; their Aſſemblies too, &amp; ſate alone in ſilence, waiting in the ſilence of my ſpirit for the Lord, and was as a travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling VVoman, pained to be delivered; yea, J was almoſt quite gone, and had even deſpaired of hope, had not the Lord had compaſſion, and been very merciful unto me, who drew near, and ſuſtained me when the night of darkneſs was over me; for it pleaſed the Lord while J was yet in patience waiting for him, to reveal his Son in me, who hath even ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and is riſen with healing in his Wings: So now in him my weary ſoul after long travel is come to find reſt and peace for evermore, which no man can take from me if J be faithful to the end: Bleſſing, and praiſes, and honor, and glory, and dominion, and thankſgiving to the Lord God of Sabbaths, and to the Lamb for ever, and ever, who hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me the peace, and the victory (in meaſure) over death, hell, and the grave; praiſes to the Lord, for his mercies fails not, but are renewed every moment towards his ſervant, and ſuch as fear him, who hath not left my ſoul in hell, neither hath he ſuffered his holy one to ſee corruption, but hath ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed my ſoul from death and the grave, into perfect liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, even to joy and gladneſs, and all ſorrovv and ſighing doth flye avvay, for the years of rejoicing is come; praiſes, endleſs praiſes, and honor and glory to him that ſitteth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne of Judgement and Mercy, vvho takes avvay the ſins of the vvorld, and ſaves his people from their ſins, that they may praiſe him together vvith one accord in the land of the living, vvho hath done vvonderfully for me that J even admire the goodneſs of God tovvards me in all his vvorks; everlaſting glorious praiſes and bleſſing to him for evermore, vvhoſe right it is, and vvhoſe vvorks praiſes him; not unto me Lord, not unto me, but unto thee, holy &amp; vviſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36430:10"/>
God over all, be all the glory and the honor. Let all that know the Lord, praiſe him above all, for his mercies endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever, who now hath brought me into fellowſhip with the Saints in light.</p>
            <p>Neighbors and Friends, Theſe things I write not unto you, to have praiſe of you, for I receive not honor from man; but that ye may know and underſtand what God hath wrought, and what he hath done for my ſoul, that all might come to praiſe the Lord, and to admire him who hath done great things in the Earth. So this is a Warning unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of you, That ye reſt not ſatisfied in any thing ſhort of Chriſt, but that ye may all even turn to the light, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the light, and walk in the light while ye have the light, leſt any be hardened through the deceitfulneſs of ſin, and ſo come ſhort of the Grace of God. So all be warned, that ye put not truſt in a falſe confidence, in a falſe faith, and in a vain hope, and ſo ye get up into a falſe joy, below Chriſt, for the end of this is weeping, mourning ſorrow and lamentation; ſo take heed how ye chooſe to follow your Prieſts, leſt ye alſo periſh with them together, being parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers with them in their ſins; ſo chooſe not to follow your own Ways, neither lean not to your own underſtandings, nor put no truſt to your own Righteouſneſs, glory not in your own Wiſdom and ſtrength, but now even all of you, come to the Light Chriſt, the Righteouſneſs of God to put him on, and ſo to put off your own righteouſneſs, that ye coming to the light, and follow the light, to have the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Law fulfilled in you, that every one of you may prove your ſelves; ſo ſearch and try your own Ways, and turn to the true light (Chriſt Jeſus) who enlightneth every man that cometh into the World, and ſee if ye can witneſs Chriſt in you; <hi>Know ye not how Chriſt is in you except ye be reprobates?</hi> I ſay, if ye know not Chriſt formed in you, if ye feel not the life of the Son of God moving and breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in you towards God; I ſay, if Chriſt be not raiſed, ye are yet in your ſins if the dead riſe not, and ſo your Faith is vain, and your Profeſſion alſo, For as many as receives
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36430:10"/>
Chriſt, receives the Righteouſneſs of God, in him receives Gods Righteouſneſs; for Chriſt is Gods Righteouſneſs; and who hath not Chriſt, their Righteouſneſs is of themſelves, and ſo are ignorant of Gods righteouſneſs, who knows not the Light, Chriſt in them, who will not come to the light, ſo will not ſubmit to the righteouſneſs of God, but would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs; yet will not ſuch people ſpeak againſt ſelf-righteouſneſs, and againſt ſelf-actings, when as all their Righteouſneſs and Works is of themſelves? How blind are theſe people, who out of their own mouth hath condemned themſelves, wherein all they do is of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Will-Worſhip to be ſeen of men, and would lay theſe things to our charge whom they call <hi>Quakers,</hi> and ſaith that we altogether ſet up Works before Chriſt, always perſwades people to Works, and to the keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is falſe; Though We perſwade people to be followers of good Works, and to the keeping of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments according to Chriſts exhortation, yet We do not turn people to Works before We turn them to Chriſt; but We firſt exhort them to believe in the light; ſo they are lyars; for this is our Meſſage, <hi>To turn people from the darkneſs to the Light, Chriſt, who lightneth every man, that they may have their works wrought in the Light Christ, who works all our works in us, and for us; and he that loves the light, brings his deeds to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt that they are wrought in God; but what is this to them who are not come unto the light, neither hath believed in the light? have they not manifeſted their ignorance, and that all their works of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are of themſelves, and that they have no other righteouſneſs, who are not come to the light;</hi> [mark, and take notice of this] <hi>That all their deeds and works are onely of themſelves wrought in darkneſs, until ſuch time as they come to be turned from the darkneſſe to the light; for that which is not wrought in the light, is wrought in darkneſſe.</hi> So hovv can ſuch eſcape the judgements of God vvho have ſo falſly accuſed us that have renounced our own Righteouſneſs, and hath vvilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36430:11"/>
ſubmitted to the Righteouſneſs of God, that We might be found in Chriſt? There is but as it were two Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, the Righteouſneſs of God, and mans Righteouſneſs, ſo until man return unto God, and comes to know how Chriſt is in him, who is Gods Righteouſneſs, all his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is of himſelf; and theſe are contrary the one to the other: So the Way to know the one from the other, is, <hi>To believe in the light, and in the light to know each from other; and walking in the light, comes to put on the Righteouſneſſe of God, and put off their own, and to deny themſelves, and then comes to ſee their own Righteouſneſſe filthy and abominable.</hi> So here is the Way of Righteouſneſs, in the Light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who lightneth every man that cometh into the World; and he that follows the Light Chriſt, puts on Righteouſneſs as a Garment; and he that doth righteouſneſs, is righteous, even as he is righteous, and he that doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God: So We who are come unto Chriſt our Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, our Light and Life, We come to be made the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God in him, and ſo in the Light wherein We have believed, comes to fulfil all righteouſneſs; and for this end, <hi>That we might be found in himn, ot having our own righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, even the righteouſneſſe which is of God by faith;</hi> many of us (who are called <hi>Quakers</hi>) have denyed our ſelves, our lives, and whatſoever was dear unto us, our Father and Mother, Husband, Wife and Children, Brethren, and Siſters, and Kinred all, Houſes, Lands and Livings, and the World too, and all the Glory and the Pleaſures of this life, who have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up the Croſs of Chriſt, that We might be counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to follow him in the Regeneration as obedient children, not faſhioning our ſelves unto this World any longer put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the former converſation which is corrupt, the old man with his deeds, that We might be renewed in the ſpirit of our mind, putting on the new man which after God is created in righteouſneſs and true holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee God, keeping the holy Commandment of our Lord Jeſus, who ſaid, <hi>If ye love me, keep my Commandments;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36430:11"/>
and if a man love me, he will keepe my ſayings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So Neighbors and Friends, it is not only a profeſſion and talking of Free-Grace, and of Juſtification by Chriſt, this will not ſerve you except ye come into the obedience of the Grace of God which brings ſalvation, and hath appeared unto all men; For the Grace of God is the Saints Teacher, which teaches them to deny all ungodlineſs and Worldly luſts, and to deny the Prieſts, to be taught of them any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; For all the children of the Lord is taught of the Lord, and in righteouſneſs they are eſtabliſhed, and great is their peace. So ye who are not turned from your Prieſts, are not taught of the Lord, who ſaid, <hi>Ceaſe ye from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi> So Friends while ye remain under them, ye are not come into the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and teachings of the Spirit of Grace and Truth which hath appeared unto all men, and teaches us to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent World: So take heed unto your ſelves, and hearken not unto your Prieſts, nor to your Diviners, who divine for money, for they deceive you; but all turn to the Light wherewith Chriſt hath enlightned you, which is truth and no lye; for there is no lye of the Truth: He that doth Truth, cometh to the Light; and he that doth evil hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, leaſt his deeds ſhould be reproved; and this is the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the Light, (ſaid Chriſt) So ſee if all your Prieſts be not in the evil, under the condemnation of the Devil who hate the Light, evil beaſts, ſlow-bellies, hating the light, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching and railing againſt it, becauſe their deeds are evil, and becauſe that they know if the people turn to the light, they will then come to ſee their deceit and covetouſneſs, and will be aſhamed of them. So Friends, take not counſel of your Prieſts, for miſchief is in their hearts, leſt vvhile ye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after them, ye come to be hardned in your ſins, and your ſences and feeling after God be taken from you, and ſo ye become paſt feeling, having your conſciences ſeared, and your hearts hardened againſt God, and then ye be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up unto a reprobate minde, to work all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36430:12"/>
with greedineſs, even with the Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Conſider Friends, Can the Prieſts ſatisfie you, and pleaſe you with vain Words onley, to talk of Free-Grace, and of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed, who are in the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs themſelves, ſo holds the Truth in unrighteouſneſs, and will not come to the light; verily Friends ye are then far ſhort of what I was when I was where ye now are, with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of God and godlineſs, but without the power and the life; for nothing then would ſatisfie me but Chriſt only; <hi>None but Chriſt, None but Chriſt,</hi> was my continual cry, to have Chriſt, how I might come to know Chriſt in me; <hi>Give me Chriſt, or I dye,</hi> to feel him near, which juſtifies and ſaves his people from their ſins, this was the dayly deſires, and the longings of my weary ſoul; <hi>had I but hold on Chriſt, let them take the world that will,</hi> (ſaid I in my heart) ſo that I might but come to know Chriſt, and to enjoy him, that I might come to live unto Chriſt, was the daily deſires of my heart and ſoul; yet though I ſought diligently after him with Tears and VVeeping, and asked the Way to Chriſt from one Prieſt unto another, to ſee if they could ſhevv me vvhere Chriſt is to be found, yet none of them could ſhevv me the Way, nor could tell me hovv to come to Chriſt. So I found no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for my ſoul from them, therefore I had no reſt day nor night from God in my ſpirit vvhile I ſought unto the Prieſts lips for counſel; for Wicked Counſellors are they all vvho turn not people to the light from the darkneſs; for Chriſt the light vvas condemnation to me vvhilſt I remained in the old nature vvith the Prieſts rebellious, and no Juſtification then, and Sanctification, and Peace, ſitting in the darkneſs, and vvalking in the darkneſs and blindneſs with the Prieſts, being then ignorant of the light vvhich Chriſt had enlightned me vvithall; ſo ſhall all who comes to knovv vvhat God is, more or leſs, ſhall firſt feel the Wrath of God revealed from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt them for their unrighteouſneſs, and ſhall ſee Wrath, and Horror, and the Vengeance of God to come upon the Head of the Wicked, even the Judgements of God coming upon that nature in them vvhich hath acted iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36430:12"/>
and tranſgreſſion, and the povver of God ſhall make the Inhabitants of the Earth to tremble; the Priſon-Houſes ſhall ſhake when the Priſoner comes forth to be ſet free, and then captivity comes to be led captive, and the ſtrong Man ſhall then be caſt out of the Houſe, and his Goods too, when Chriſt who is ſtronger then he comes to be revealed in them; all theſe things ſhall be before Gods ſalvation, and peace which paſſeth all underſtanding, be witneſſed; I ſay, They ſhall know a day of trouble, and of howling, and of bitter lamentation, (ſuch as never was) for their Wickedneſs and Tranſgreſſions againſt God, before they come to know the Lord God as he is, vvho vvill render Vengeance in flames of fire upon his Enemies, and upon the Head of all that do Wickedly; for Chriſt comes to deſtroy the Works of the Devil. So bleſſed and happy they are that abide faithful e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the end, who are willing to bear the indignation of the Lord becauſe that they have ſinned againſt him, until he ariſe and plead their cauſe. But wo unto the Prieſts who daub with untempered Morter, crying peace, peace to the people that ſtop into their mouths, but prepares VVar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us who cannot ſtop into their mouths; ſo upon them, and upon their people, ſhall the day of the Lord come as a thief in the night, and no peace ſhall then be to them, though they now cry peace, peace; even then when they ſhall ſay peace and ſafety, ſhall ſudden deſtruction come upon them, as Travel upon a VVoman with child, and they ſhall not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape; then ſhall they know that their Faith was never im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to them for righteouſneſs from God; ſo what is this to them, or to the r people, to talk of an imputed righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who doth not believe in the light, but hates the light, and will not come to the light; ſo what is this to them? for <hi>Abraham</hi> (unto whom righteouſneſs was imputed) believed God, and left his own countrey, and went out, not knowing whither he went, and was obedient in following the Lord; ſo his Faith was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs: But what is this to the Prieſts and to their Followers, who knows not <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith, which was made perfect by VVorks; For
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36430:13"/>
Faith without VVorks is dead; if a man ſay he hath Faith, and hath not VVorks, can Faith ſave him? VVas not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> juſtified by VVorks vvhen be offered <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſon upon the Altar? Here all may ſee how Faith vvrought vvith his VVorks, vvho have an eye to ſee vvithall; ſo by VVorks was Faith made perfect; for every Tree is known by his Fruit; a good Tree cannot bring forth evil Fruit, neither can an evil Tree bring forth good Fruit; ſo we know the Prieſts by their Fruits, who are of that vvicked one vvhich cannot bring forth good Fruit, vvho are the evil Trees which cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers the ground; fruitleſs Trees, rendred of all people uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, who out of the evil Treaſure of their heart, brings forth that which is evil; ſo they being evil, knows not to give good things unto their Followers; not that I in any vviſe, out of ill wil or malice, goes about to accuſe the prieſts, or any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple elſe, God knows that I ſpeak not in contempt unto any, but would take people off putting truſt in man, and that they might come to know the Lord, and in him to truſt that all might come to be taught of the Lord, that he might teach them himſelf of his VVayes, who teaches his people to profit: And this is my end, <hi>To turn all unto Chriſt the light, who lightneth every man, and that people might try their Prieſts by their fruits; for if they were of the good Tree, they could not bring forth evil fruit: And doth this offend either Prieſt or people, To exhort all to try them by their fruits, and to turn from them that brings forth evil fruit, unto the light of Chriſt in them, who lightneth every man that cometh into the world, that they may come to be engrafted into Chriſt, that in him they may come to bring forth good fruit; if they abide in the light, and walk in the light as he is in the light, they cannot bring forth evil fruit; for he that abideth in Chriſt the light, ſinneth not, but out of the good Treaſure of his heart, bringeth forth that which is good.</hi> So I ſay, my end is, <hi>That all, both Prieſts and people, might come to repentance, and every man come to be aſhamed of his own way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that they have choſen, and ſo every one, both Prieſts and people, might return unto Chriſt the light, who lightneth every man, and wills not the death of a ſinner, but would have all men, both prieſts
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36430:13"/>
and people, to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth, who is ſet for ſalvation to the ends of the earth, that all people might come to the light, and to the brightneſſe of his riſing, both prieſts and people, that ſo all might come to be taught of the Lord, who teaches his people to profit, that ſo none might follow after a people which cannot profit.</hi> The Prieſts if they were of the good Tree which cannot bring forth evil fruit, would not be aſhamed to be tryed by their fruits; but they being of the evil Tree, which cannot bring forth good Fruit, are aſhamed to have their deeds brought to the light, neither will they come to the light to prove their calling and Miniſter-ſhip before the people, leaſt they ſhould have ſhame of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and practice before all the people, their practice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to all the holy Prophets and Apoſtles of Chriſt: So it is plain, They being of the evil Tree which brings forth evil Fruit, cannot profit the people at all; ſo the people who follow them are ever learning, yet never able to come to the knowledge of the truth by them.</p>
            <p>So whileſt I followed the Prieſts, though I diligently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired unto them after the Lord, yet I found him not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſought unto a people which could not profit, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I did not attain to the thing which I ſought for unto them, ſo turned from them, finding no profit by them; and then within a little while after this, the light of the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to riſe in obſcurity, and my eyes was opened, and then through the mercy and love of the Lord, I was turned from the darkneſs to the light of Chriſt in me, and then my mind was turned from following the prieſts, from doating on them, and my heart was changed; for now in the light of the Lord <hi>I</hi> ſee light, and how I have wandered, walking in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without light; but now my light is come, the light ſprings, and the day dawns, for the day-ſtar is riſen in my heart, and the clouds of darkneſs flies away; for the glory of the Lord is revealed, and the clear light now ſhineth out of darkneſs, and Chriſt is riſen; ſo I have found him of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Law and the Porphets did write; For God who commands the light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath ſhined
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36430:14"/>
into my heart, to give me the light of the Knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, even ſo hath it pleaſed the Lord to reveal his Son in me; bleſſing and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous praiſes to the Lord God everlaſting, and to the Lamb whoſe right it is, &amp; now I plainly ſee, that in vain is the help of man, their counſels is nought but deceit and hypocriſie, and ſhall be confounded, their Wiſdom is fooliſhneſs with God, who will deſtroy the Wiſdom of the Wiſe: So I do deny all the teachings of the Prieſts any longer, for it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lord that teaches me to profit; for through his Word of Truth which I have hid in my heart, am I become wiſer then all my Teachers; the Lord is my Shepherd, I ſhall not want, who is now appearing and riſen in this the day of his glorious power, to teach his people himſelf of his Ways, by his Eternal Infallible Spirit of Light, Life and Power, which ſhines into their hearts, and gives them the Knowledge of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, who enlightneth every man that cometh into the World, that all men believing in the light, may come to know both the Father and the Sonne, whom to know is life eternal, all coming to the light; this is he that reveals the Father. So Friends, the light is your Way if ye love it; <hi>I am the way,</hi> ſaith Chriſt the Light, who lightneth every man; <hi>No man comes to the Father but by me; no man knows the Father, but the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him.</hi> But Friends, wil a profeſſion of Words &amp; a talk of knowing the Father and the Son, and a boaſting of Free-Grace in words, be ſufficient to any of you who are turned from the light within, into darkneſs, to follow the Prieſts and blind guides which cannot profit you? ſo ye are not taught by Grace who heap up Teachers unto your ſelves, having itching ears, ye have turned your ears from the light, from the truth, ſo ye are turned from the Grace of God which brings ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hath appeared unto all men; and what is the Free-Grace of God unto any of you, who turn the Free-Grace of God into wantonneſs, who are not taught by it to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your ſins, and to deny all ungodlineſs and Worldly luſts, and to live a godly and a gracious life? ſo are not come into
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36430:14"/>
obedience to God, but are ſtiff-necked and rebellious, and are alive unto ſin, and all ungodlineſs and Worldly luſts, ſo ye are free from Grace: And ſo what ſuch a vain, fooliſh, rotten, ſtinking profeſſion is this of yours, people, who cryes, <hi>Free-Grace, Free-Grace, nothing but by Free-Grace are we ſaved?</hi> O bluſh for ſhame, and be ye all horribly afraid for your impudency and lying againſt God, as to ſay ye are ſaved by Grace, when as ye are yet in your ſins, and will not receive the Gift of Gods Free-Grace, which hath been ſo largely and ſo freely tendered unto every one of you from the God of all Grace, and hath even appeared in you all, and to you all, and yet ye have refuſed to incline your ear, and hear: For this is the Grace of God, and the great love of God towards you all, That he hath given you a light, which light in you all tells you that ye ſhould not lye, nor ſwear, nor be covetous, nor be drunk, nor that ye ſhould not envy, nor hate, nor diſſemble, but lets you ſee that you ſhould love the Lord God with all your heart, and your Neighbor as your ſelves; ſo ſee if ye be come to this: Theſe things ye know, and happy are ye if ye do them, otherwiſe ye are not ſaved by grace, but doth come ſhort of the grace of God, to be taught of God, if ye be overtaken with lying, or ſwearing, or with covetouſneſs, or drunkenneſs, with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying, or hatred, or diſſembling, and the like, which are the Fruits of the fleſh: So ye do deſpite to the Spirit of grace (whatſoever your profeſſion in Words to the contrary be) who are found here: But unto us who have believed in the light, the grace of God which hath appeared unto all men, teaches us to deny all ungodlineſs and Worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent World: And ſo by grace are we ſaved, not of our ſelves, it is the gift of God; for by grace we ſtand, and by grace we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſalvation through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: And this in my meaſure I witneſs.</p>
            <p>But Friends, Will ye ſin becauſe grace hath abounded and hath appeared in you all? Conſider, Is that the meaſure of the gift of the grace of God which teaches ye to ſin againſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36430:15"/>
God, and to be proud and covetous, to lye, and to ſwear, to envy, and to hate, and to be drunk, and to ſight, to be light, vain and wanton, to luſt, murder, and to deſtroy, and to live in all the cuſtoms and faſhions of the Heathen? God forbid: Nay, but that Spirit which brings forth theſe things is the Spirit of Devils, and not from the Spirit of grace: So you who are not ſubject to the Spirit of grace, but brings forth the like Fruits, as aboveſaid, are not come to grace, ſo cannot grow in grace, from grace to grace, who are not taught by grace to deny all unrighteouſneſs whatſoever: So what have ye to do as to take my Words in your mouths, (ſaith the Lord) who talk and make a profeſſion of free grace? What have ye to do to take my Name in your mouths? for the Way of grace and truth ye have deſpiſed; yea verily, ye have done deſpite to the Spirit of grace, and hath caſt my Law behind your backs, ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Truly Friends I cannot ſow pillows under your arm-holes, or under your elbows, as your greedy hireling-Prieſts do, who cry peace, peace; but I ſhall deal plainly with you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will hear or forbear: For this is the free grace of God, and the love by grace, that God hath given us of his Son, Hath ſent his own Son a light into the World, that all men through him might believe and know the truth, who enlightneth every man that cometh into the World: And he that is not faithful and obedient to the pure light in his conſcience, which comes from the Son of God, and lets him ſee his evil deeds, and that he ſhould not ſin at all, he hears not God; ſo whoſoever ſins againſt the light, wrongs his own ſoul. To the light in all your conſciences (people of all profeſſions) I ſpeak.</p>
            <p>And Friends and Neighbors, While I was one with you in profeſſion, with a profeſſion of God and of Chriſt in my mouth, without the life and poſſeſſion, ye loved me, and did ſpeak well of me, I being then one with you in the World; for the World loves its own; and many of you rejoiced to ſee me; and Friends, What am I now become your Enemy, becauſe God hath put it into my heart to chooſe the better
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36430:15"/>
part, who hath had mercy on me, and hath choſen me out of the World to be a Veſſel unto honour; who hath redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med me from amongſt the Sons of men, to bear his Name among the Heathen in truth and righteouſneſs, according to my meaſure, who hath given me life in the blood of the everlaſting Covenant of Light and Peace; who hath pluckt my Feet out of the myre and clay, and hath ſet them in a plain Way, that I may for ever walk in the Light of the Lord, where no occaſion of ſtumbling is? But now Friends, Where is all your love ye had towards me? Is it all loſt and gone? Doe ye not love the World, and few the things of Jeſus Chriſt? for they that love the World, hath not the love of God in them. And ſince it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in me, who hath choſen me and called me by his grace out from my Fathers Houſe, &amp; from my Kinred alſo, do not even many of you hate me without a cauſe, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſcorns me, and even wags your heads at me, and gazes upon me, and ſaith, <hi>Lo this is he?</hi> and ſome ſayes that they pitty me, and are ſorry for me that I ſhould chooſe a Way that is ſo contemptible and deſpiſed amongſt men. Friends, To the Light of Chriſt in all your conſciences I ſpeak; What evil have I done ſince I owned Chriſt Jeſus my everlaſting Light, to be my Teacher, whereof I may be aſhamed? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me. Is it an unrighteous thing with you to chooſe to follow that which is good in the ſight of God, and of all honeſt men, even to follovv after righteouſneſs and truth, and to turn from darkneſs unto the light, and from the power of Satan unto God? And vvas not the Way of God alvvaies deſpiſed and rejected of men, even Chriſt Jeſus, the Light, the Way, the Truth and the Life? Have ye never read that the Stone vvhich the Builders rejected and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that the ſame is become the Head of the corner? A man of ſorrovvs, deſpiſed and rejected of men; and how that <hi>Herod</hi> and his mighty men of VVar ſet him at nought? So it is poſſible, that that which is highly eſteemed amongſt men, may be abomination in the ſight of God; and that which is chiefly deſpiſed amongſt men, and ſet at nought
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36430:16"/>
with them, may be chiefly owned, and highly eſtemed with God, and precious; <hi>For my wayes are not as your wayes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are your wayes as my wayes, ſaith the Lord:</hi> So it is plain, That whoſoever will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer perſecution, and muſt be hated of all men; For whoſoever departs from iniquity, makes himſelf a prey to the Heathen, and becomes a reproach and a by-word among the people, for righteouſneſs ſake. So ye that ſay ye pitty me, and are ſorry for me, this I ſay, Be not troubled for me, but pitty your ſelves &amp; your children; ſo weep not for me becauſe my Father according to the fleſh hath ſhut his doors againſt me, who hath deſpiſed and forſaken his ovvn child, contrary to nature, as one not worthy to inhabit under his roof, who may be aſhamed of his profeſſion, a hard hearted man, even without natural affections, who hath exceeded the Heathen (vvho knovv not God) in his rage and cruelty; I pray God that it may not be laid to his charge: For my part I am vvilling to ſuffer the loſs of all things, if the will of God be ſo, rather then to turn from the righteous vvay of the Lord my God, chooſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon now when I am come to years: And now if God ſhould even deal with him who is my natural Father, according as he hath dealt with me, as to ſhut him out of his Kingdom for ever, vvere it not juſt and equal? but far be it from me to deſire any mans deſtruction, but rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that the thoughts of his heart may be forgiven him, that he might come to repentance; but truly this I know from the Lord, that if he come not to repentance, that vvhat he hath done againſt me he ſhall find it heavy in the dreadful day of the Lords Vengeance, when he comes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard him according unto his VVorks: Truly when I think of this, my ſoul even mourns and vveeps for him, vvho now (<hi>Dives</hi>-like) is feeding upon his many diſhes, and hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten God that made him; for I told him before that he put me from him, That I was willing to abide with him, and to ſerve him faithfully, as it becomes a Son to honor his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36430:16"/>
and ſaid, that it was fitting for him to ſuffer me to ſtay with him in his Houſe until ſuch times as he could find any unfaithfulneſs in me in what things as he ſhould pleaſe to commit unto my care, and then he might (after that he could convince me of unfaithfulneſs) have ſome ground of cauſe why he would put me from him; but to put me away without cauſe, for a thing of nought, this is a thing altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unjuſt, contrary to all reaſon and equity: And as for any part of diſobedience on my part towards him, I know of none, unleſs refuſing to follow after the Prieſts, as he would have had me; and I told him that I could not find any profit by them, and why would he therefore have me to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after a people that cannot profit? For God hath ſaid, That they ſhall not profit the people at all: And this ſhall all people find true by woful experience, That they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver profit by them while they follow them; for I would as gladly have profited by them as any, if it had been poſſible; but the Prieſts being a covetous, wicked, lying people, a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Vipers, who never was ſent of God, how ſhould they therefore profit the people at all? as by the Scriptures of truth I can prove them to be lyars and deceivers, all out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and of the Apoſtles, and it is not requiſite that we ſhould follow lyars, and deceivers, and blind guides; ſo I could not but turn from them when I ſaw their wickedneſs and lying againſt God, and ſo in this thing it was better for me to obey God rather then my parents according to the fleſh, it being a matter of conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; and it had been but fitting I ſhould have had my liberty of conſcience towards God to worſhip; but my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Father would not ſuffer me to have this liberty, but hath ſhut his doors againſt me, and hath put me from him upon this account, For not following the Prieſts any longer: So hath he not even hated me without cauſe? when as both before he put me away, and ſince, I have proved the Prieſts to be lyars and deceivers, according to the Scriptures: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath he not herein exceeded the Heathen, for a hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted man againſt his own child? let all honeſt men judge;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36430:17"/>
for the very firſt day I went unto a meeting of the people of God, the ſame day at night I returned again unto my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe, and the doors was ſhut againſt me; and then I called unto my Brother <hi>William,</hi> and bad him let me into the Houſe; and he told me that he durſt not let me into the Houſe I asked him Why? He ſaid, That his Father had ſent all his children and ſervants to bed, &amp; that he went through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Houſe himſelf to ſee that all the doors was lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bolted againſt me, and did charge them all that if I did come, not any of them to let me into the Houſe; if they did any of them, he ſaid that he would turn them alſo out of the doors with me. So <hi>William</hi> told me theſe things, and that he durſt not let me into the Houſe; ſo unto this day I remain a ſufferer for righteouſneſs ſake; and truly I believe that I ſhould not have put pen to paper in reference as to all my ſufferings from my natural Father, had I not heard how he hath reported it that I ran from him, and the like: So for the right informing all peoples underſtandings, (as to the truth of this matter) I have briefly in few Words decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſomething of what hath been done by him towards me, and of what Words paſſed between us; but I might have intimated much more of his rage and cruelty, &amp; ſore uſuage of me, but that I am againſt laying open nakedneſs, and have onely cleared my own innocency as touching falſe reports of running from my Fathers Houſe, and the like, as alſo his own Family and others can witneſs againſt him to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary for me; if they wil but teſtifie.</p>
            <p>So let him conſider, and look back, and ſee what he hath done againſt the innocent that ſeeks not his own, who ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no revenge, but ſuffereth all things, endureth all things, and envieth not, but in the peace which the World cannot give nor take away, reſts ſatisfied in his Fathers love from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and ſo refers his cauſe unto him that ſeeth in ſecret, who rewardeth openly, and taketh vengeance; <hi>For vengeance is mine,</hi> ſaith the Lord: So I have boldneſs towards God in all my ſufferings and tribulations, yea verily I have the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36430:17"/>
of a good conſcience towards God and man herein; Gods Witneſs in me, even the Spirit of truth, which bears witneſs to my ſpirit that I ſuffer for well doing; and who ſhall then condemn me? And becauſe I cannot for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-ſake worſhip the beaſt, nor follow the blind guides any longer, I am perſecuted and forſaken of Father and Mother, and of Brethren and Siſters, and of Kinred too, and theſe things have they done unto me that the Scriptures might be fulfilled according to Chriſts Words, who ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men for my ſake; and marvel not if the World hate you, for it hated me before it hated you; if ye were of the World, the World would love you, for the World loves its own, but becauſe I have choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hates you, becauſe ye are not of the world, even as I am not of the world,</hi> ſaid Chriſt to them that followed him in the regeneration, who turned people from the darkneſs to the Light, Chriſt; <hi>And he that forſaketh not Father and Mother, Brethren and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Husband, Wife, or children, and his own life too, for my ſake and the Goſpel,</hi> (ſaid Chriſt) <hi>he cannot be my diſciple; and he that taketh not up his Croſs, and followeth not after me, he is not worthy of me; but every one that hath left Father, or Mother, Brethren, or Siſters, Husband, Wife, or Children, or Houſe, or Lands for my Names ſake, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſpel, let him rejoice that he is counted worthy to ſuffer it,</hi> (ſaid the Lord Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>for he ſhall not loſe his reward, but ſhall receive an hundred-fold in this life, and in the world to come everlaſting life.</hi> So it is evident, That whoſoever will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer; For he that departs from iniquity, makes himſelf a prey to the wicked, and to the unrighteous and ſinners. So Friends, think it not ſtrange I run not with you to the ſame exceſs of riot into all uncleanneſs and filthineſs; and ſorrow not for me, for the ſorrow of the World works death; ſo ſpeak not evil of the things ye know not, leaſt ye ſpeak evil againſt God; and though I am counted as the off-ſcouring of all things unto this day, and hath not whereon to lay my head, being forſaken of Father and of Mother, and counted as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36430:18"/>
one not worthy to live, nor to inhabit under them, who could not have ſo much as a ſervants place under them; for I told my Father before he put me from him, That I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to abide with him, and to ſerve him faithfully, and to labour with my hands in the thing that is good; yet would he not ſuffer me to inhabit under him; but in all this what evil have I done? So I have comfort towards God, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his cruel uſuage of me, and though Father and Mother hath forſaken me, yet the Lord hath not forſaken me, neither left me comfortleſs, but hath been with me in all my afflictions to ſupport me; and though they through the hardneſs of their hearts hath had no pitty on me but I was even caſt out for righteouſneſs ſake, as though I had been ſome great tranſgreſſor; Where are my Accuſers? If I have done evil, let them bear witneſs of the evil; but if well, for cleaving unto the Lord, why are they ſo offended in me? I could even deſire that the Lord would not reward them as they have rewarded me, who are even without natural affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and without any pitty towards me; yet the Lord hath had pitty, becauſe his mercies fails not, who in his favour hath redeemed me, and hath had compaſſion when no eye pittyed; for he hath ſaid it; Thou hadſt a little ſtrength, and haſt truſted in me, therefore I will never leave thee nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee. Thou haſt hated iniquity, and loved righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, therefore walk before me, and be thou perfect, and I will help thee, I will be with thee, and go before thee all the Way that thou ſhalt go. So in the Arms of his everlaſting Love doth the Lord carry me, and in his hand doth he hide me, that ſo in the pure love of God I might remain under the ſhadow of his Wings for evermore, and in his Name to truſt, which is a ſtrong Tower for the righteous to flye unto; for God hath given me an entrance into the eternal inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Saints in light: Surely I have made a good choice, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord for evermore, who hath put it into my heart as to chooſe the good Way, and the fear of the Lord, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs. So I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36430:18"/>
am perſwaded in my heart to cleave unto the Lord my God with my whole heart, that the Lamb of God I may follow whereſoever he goes, though I dye with him, bearing his re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proach; for through Chriſt that ſtrengthens me, I am more then a Conqueror, and have in meaſure conquered Death, Hell, and the Grave, and through Faith have overcome the World, ſo hath right to eat of the Tree of Life; glorious praiſes to God for ever, whoſe Works now praiſes him: And though I am become a ſtranger unto my Fathers Houſe, and to my Kinred alſo, and hath not whereon to lay my head, yet God hath prepared an Houſe for me, and hath brought me into his Houſe of Love, even into everlaſting Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, a ſpiritual houſe to worſhip him in, hath he even prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red eternally in the Heavens, which remaineth for ever; and he will never ſhut me out of his Houſe, but he hath given me within his Houſe, and within his Walls, a place and a Name, better then of Sons and of Daughters, an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Habitation, and a Name that ſhall not be cut off; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, endleſs praiſes to God in the Higheſt. This hath the Lord done for his Names ſake; and how can I forbear to tell of what God hath done for my ſoul? If I ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his wondrous Works before men, to tell of his wonderful Works, it had bin better for me never to have bin born; Who hath even filled me with the Riches of his glory in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; who hath taken me out of the Olive-Tree, which is wild by nature, and now hath he grafted me (contrary to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) into a good Olive-Tree; ſo in my meaſure I am come to know him that was from the beginning; yea, I am in him that is true, who is the true God, and eternal life, being planted into Chriſt, that I may bring forth Fruit unto God, who in times paſt was an alien and a ſtranger to the Life of God; but am now through the grace of God, no more a ſtranger, but a Fellow-Citizen with the Saints, and of the Houſhold of God, being built upon the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Chriſt himſelf being the chief Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-ſtone, in whom all the Building fitly framed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36430:19"/>
growth unto an holy Temple in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Therefore all Friends and Neighbors, having taſted that the Lord is gracious and full of compaſſion towards them that truſt in him, I cannot but even in bowels of compaſſion beſeech you even to return unto the Lord with your whole heart, that ye may love him with all your heart; ye who hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger after righteouſneſs, ye who would eat of the bread of life, come in to the light even ye who are ready to die &amp; pine away w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> hunger for want of bread, turn in hither, for in my Fathers houſe is even Bread enough for all that is hungry indeed, that ye may freely eat of, &amp; live for ever; if it were not ſo, I would not invite you; but ſeeing and feeling that it is even ſo, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but beſeech you. So every one that is a-thirſt, come and take of the Fountain of the Water of Life freely, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will, and buy Wine and Milk without money and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out price; ſo ſpend not your money for that which is not Bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfies not; my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther giveth you the true bread, and whoſoever eats thereof ſhall live for ever, and be ſatisfied; and the Fountain of the Water of Life is ſet open, that whoſoever is a-thirſt may freely drink, and be filled. And the Bread of God is he that cometh down from Heaven, who lightneth every man that cometh into the World, that all men through him might be ſaved, who filleth the hungry with good things, but the rich he ſends empty away. So all Friends believe in the light, come unto the light, leaſt ye dye in your ſins; for the Lord hath no pleaſure that ye ſhould dye in your ſins, but rather that ye ſhould turn from your evil Ways, and live unto him, that ſo ye might know the Way of life from the VVays of death. As ye come to own the light of God in you, as ye love it, it will teach you the right VVay, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs; a wiſe man vvill firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſs thereof, that he may come to knovv the Lord, and find reſt and peace in him, vvhich the vvorld cannot give. So Friends, if ye would know thoſe things, and come to have reſt and peace in Chriſt Jeſus, then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36430:19"/>
ye muſt come to the light wherewith ye are enlightned: Therefore all mind the light of God in you which ſhines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your hearts, for the light is your vvay if ye love it; ſo if ye chooſe to follow the Light, Chriſt, this is he that reveals the Father, whom no man knovvs but the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him; this is he in whom the vveary comes to find reſt and peace: So as every one comes into the obedience of the light, he comes to ſee the Kingdom of God, and hath right to enter into the Kingdom; and if yee vvait in the light but a vvhile in patience, ye ſhall ſee that the Kingdom of God is come nigh; <hi>Know ye not that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven is within you?</hi> So all in the light wait for the Kingdom of God to be revealed in you, which ſtands not in vvords, but in righteouſneſs, and in the truth; ſo if even ye knovv the Kingdom of God, ye ſhall know it within you, a holy Kingdom holy and everlaſting, into which nothing that maketh a lye, or is unclean, ſhall enter; For bleſſed and holy are they that are counted vvorthy to enter therein, vvhich have not defiled themſelves with VVomen. Novv therefore Friends, as ye deſire the ſalvation of your ſouls, wait in the light, even in the holy and juſt principle of God, in that vvhich is holy, which convinces of ſin, and of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, and lets you ſee your ſins, and all that ever ye have done, if ye vvill but hear and incline your ear; and as ye own the light, to be taught of the Lord, there ſhall ye come to know Chriſt the Saviour of your ſouls, who is come to ſave his people from their ſins, and to ſeek and to ſave that vvhich is loſt. So here is the vvay of the Lord, in the light, even the true and living vvay; but if ye draw back after the Prieſts, ye have rejected the Lord, to be taught of the Lord, ſo ye cannot eſcape the damnation of Hell, ſo ſhall never witneſs to be taught of the Lord in the meaſure of light, who have done deſpite to the Spirit of grace, ſo it is like ye ſhall never know Gods ſalvation, profeſs what you can in words of knowing him or his ſalvation; For God is light, and he is not known but in the light; ſo they that are not in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36430:20"/>
light, who knows not the light, are in darkneſs even until now, and ſo knows not the vvay of the Lord, for darkneſs comprehends him not, nor his light and they that be in the darkneſs, knows not whither they go, nor at what they ſtumble, becauſe that darkneſs hath blinded their eyes.</p>
            <p>Therefore all Friends and Neighbors, ye that have known me after the fleſh, I beſeech you in Chriſts ſtead to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God, and even now while ye have yet a little time in the body, haſt to meet the Lord in the manifeſtation of the Spirit of Light from God: <hi>For that which may be known of God is manifeſt in you, and God hath even ſhewed it unto you.</hi> So here is your vvay to know God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, if ever ye come to know him, vvhom to know is life eternal; For there is no other vvay but by that of God in you: So if ye will indeed own the right vvay, the good vvay, vvherein dvvelleth righteouſneſs, then come in to the light Chriſt, vvho lightneth every man, and even novv while ye have the light, believe in the light, that ye may be the children of the light, and vvalk in the light, as he is in the light, that the blood of Chriſt may clenſe you from all ſin; and then if ye abide in the light, ye ſhall continue in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in the Son, ſo ſhall ye have Fellowſhip vvith the Saints in light, vvhom the VVorld knovvs not, of vvhom the VVorld is not vvorthy, that henceforth ye may no more knovv me after the fleſh onely, but in the ſpirit, as ye come to be faithful unto the Lord in your meaſures of the light of Chriſt, where ye may feel me, and read me, and knovv me vvho am unknovvn unto the VVorld, yet vvell knovvn to the children of light, vvho in the light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt doth continue, and abides vvith God, and vvalks in the light, as he is in the light; For the children of light hath Fellovvſhip one vvith another in the light which unites their hearts together in one: But vvith the unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful VVorks of darkneſs vve have no Fellovvſhip; and here in the light, in the truth, though ten thouſand times ten
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36430:20"/>
thouſand; yet all one in the light, even in Chriſt Jeſus, who walks not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit. So Friends, by this I ſhall know that ye love me, and that ye love the Truth, as many as can receive my Teſtimony, and keeps my Fathers Commandments; For the Teſtimony is not mine, but his who hath choſen me to bear vvitneſs of him unto many; but if I bear vvitneſs of my ſelf, my vvitneſs is not true; there is one that beareth witneſs, and I know that the witneſs that he witneſſes is true; for I can of my own ſelf do nothing, yet through Chriſt that ſtrengthens me, I can do all things; For I ſeek not my own, but the things of Jeſus Chriſt, that I may do the will of God who hath choſen me out of the VVorld, to follow him in the regeneration, where the VVorld ſeeth me not, nor knows me not; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World hates me, and ſcorns me, VVhy? becauſe I am not of the VVorld, ſo the VVorld cannot receive my ſayings, they hear me not, becauſe they are not of God; for I receive not Teſtimony from man, but theſe things I ſpeak that ye might believe the truth, not by way of boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to exalt ſelf, or to puff up, for all boaſting is excluded, and ſelf-ends condemned with the Light of Truth; ſo a VVitneſs in my meaſure I ſtand eternally againſt all ſelfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for ſelf is of the Devil, and all proud boaſtings, which Chriſt comes to deſtroy. But,</p>
            <p>Theſe things (Neighbours and Friends) I write unto you that ye may come to know where reſt and true peace is, and not to exalt ſelf, that ye might praiſe me, but theſe things I declare, to the end, <hi>That ye may all be awakened to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, that ye might be ſaved, and believe what good things God hath in ſtore for them that fear him, &amp; love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his appearance, and believing in the light, ye may have life, and that every wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoul may be comforted, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome to find reſt as he comes into the obedience of the light, that the righteous God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er all might have his glory, who is the Author and Finiſher of every good Work the firſt and the laſt, God bleſſed for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36430:21"/>So all friends in the love of the truth receive this into your hearts with meekneſs and fear, which was given me from the Lord in the ſpirit, to write as a Teſtimony from the Lord to my Nation, Countrey, and People, for the Seed of Gods ſake throughout all the VVorld where this may come, was I moved of the Lord God from the love of the Spirit, which are the very breathings of my ſoul for my Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Countrey, and People, that they might be ſaved and hid in the day of the Lords wrath; but my deſire is, That the wicked one in you may be deſtroyed, and what ſoever work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unrighteouſneſs and deceit, unto which I ſay <hi>Wo,</hi> that ye may be ſeparated from all unrighteouſneſs; therefore keep your ſelves to that of God in you, that the wicked one touch you not, and from all idolatry; and ſo will the old man with his deeds come to be put off, when the Juſt comes to liberty, when Chriſt comes to have the preheminence, and rules, whoſe right it is. So Friends, take unto you the whole Armor of God, even the Armor of Light, as it comes to be put on, ye will be able to reſiſt all the fiery darts of the Devil; I ſay, As there is a watching and a waiting in the light of Chriſt Jeſus for the teachings of God in the Spirit, the luſts of the fleſh, and fleſhly confidences withers and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes away, and the hidden man of the heart comes to be felt and witneſſed, as there is an abiding in the Croſſe of Chriſt, ſo ye come to dye unto ſinne, and to be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to the VVorld, and to live unto God.</p>
            <p>Therefore all waite, that yee may have Bread to feed upon which gives life to the Soule, which is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and health to every weary Soul who comes to feed upon the living Immortal Bread which comes downe from GOD out of Heaven, ſhall live for ever. And bleſſed for evermore they are who hunger after this, for they ſhall be ſatisfied: As many as comes to eat of this Bread, and receives it into them, they ſhall grow up as Trees of Righteouſneſs, the planting of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36430:21"/>
Lord. So let every one that nameth the Name of CHRIST, depart from Iniquity, and follow the Light, and believe in the Light while ye have the Light, that ye may be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſſe and Truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Rawlinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
